Finding Aid for Michigan Environmental Council records, 1925-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Environmental Council records
1925-2012
1980-2005
Michigan Environmental Council.
93847 Aa 2
The Lansing-based Michigan Environmental Council (MEC) formed in 1980 to coordinate lobbying and other member activities, distribute information, and monitor the environmental policies of state government. More recently, the council has focused almost exclusively on distributing information, directing funding, and building broad consensus on land use issues. The MEC records include information on significant environmental issues in Michigan as well as administrative papers pertaining to the council's operation.
57.5 linear feet
1.41 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the Michigan Environmental Council (donor no. 8139 ) in various accessions beginning in 1993.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Environmental Council (MEC) is a 501(3) organization that was created in 1980 at the urging of Ken Sikkema, director of the West Michigan Environmental Action Council. The original idea seems to have come out of discussions between Sikkema and Grant Trigger. In Sikkema's view, Michigan's environmental movement at that time was losing its effectiveness. After meeting many of its goals in the 1970s, economic problems in 1979 and 1980 had made it more difficult for existing environmental organizations to keep up lobbying activities. The West Michigan Environmental Council, East Michigan Environmental Council, Detroit Audubon Society, Flint Environmental Action Team, Michigan Audubon Society, and the Mackinac Chapter of the Sierra Club agreed to work together to build an effective coordinating organization based in Lansing. The six organizations created the council and hired Grant Trigger, an environmental engineer, as its first director.
In 1983, Carol Dansereau, a lawyer, became director of the council. (David Dempsey had served for a time between Trigger and Dansereau.) Under Dansereau, the council changed its emphasis somewhat, emphasizing lobbying as well as providing information directly to individuals through the MEC newsletter (the Michigan Environmental Report), which began publication in January 1984. The council's total membership grew to 17 organizations by the time Dansereau left in 1986.
David Stead then assumed the executive director position and continued the council's emphasis on lobbying during his tenure from 1987 until 1992. He was then succeeded by Carol Misseldine who in turn served until 1996. Under her guidance, the group continued to lobby on behalf of its member organization and provide timely information about environmental issues to members and its newsletter subscribers. In 1994, MEC launched the Land Stewardship Initiative and for the first time in its history, the organization devoted itself to a single (albeit broadly defined) goal. Thus, land use--and a host of related issues--became the focus of subsequent MEC activities and led to the hiring of Julie Stoneman in 1994 as its first Land Programs Director. By the time Misseldine stepped down in 1996, MEC had 21 full and associate member organizations.
Lana Pollack, a former Michigan State Senator and founder of Michigan Monthly magazine, became president of the council in 1996 and served in that capacity through 2008. Her tenure witnessed MEC undergo vast changes in organizational structure and the expand its Land Stewardship Initiative to incorporate principles of Smart Growth, transportation design, and healthy community planning. During this period, full time MEC staff grew from five to twelve; the organizational budget increased from $320,000 to $2.3 million, and MEC came to represent 70 groups with a combined membership of approximately 200,000 Michigan citizens. In addition to lobbying, the council engaged in extensive coalition-building activities that resulted, among other things, in a ban on oil drilling below the Great Lakes and the passage in 1998 and 2002 of environmental bond issues. After a dozen years of leading MEC, Pollack was succeeded on January 1, 2009 by Chris Kolb. Additional information on the Michigan Environmental Council may be found online at http://www.environmentalcouncil.org/.
The Michigan Environmental Council records depict the incremental growth of one of Michigan's pre-eminent environmental organizations. In addition to administrative records dealing with the council's operation, the record group also contain information on key environmental issues, major council initiatives, and MEC members. These records therefore will be of value to those interested in the environmental movement, Michigan legislative process, and the development of non-profit organizations.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Dempsey, Dave, 1957-; Energy conservation--Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Great Lakes (North America)--Environmental conditions.; Hazardous wastes--Michigan.; Land use--Michigan.; Michigan Environmental Council.; Mines and mineral resources--Michigan.; Pesticides--Government policy--Michigan.; Pollack, Lana, 1942-; Refuse and refuse disposal--Michigan.; Water rights--Michigan.; Groundwater--Pollution--Michigan.; Wetland conservation--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Conservation of material resources--Michigan.; Great Lakes (North America)--Environmental conditions.; Groundwater--Pollution--Michigan.; Michigan Environmental Council.; Water pollution--Michigan.; Wetlands--Michigan.
Contributors:
Dempsey, Dave, 1957-; Pollack, Lana, 1942-
Genre Terms:
Digital file formats.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files series consists of two sub-series, 1980-1993 and 1993-1996 (both of which include earlier background materials), and each is further divided into "General Files" and "Issue Files." In both sub-series, the General Files deal with the administration of the council and include miscellaneous correspondence and papers relating to member and non-member organizations as well as government bodies. The 1993-1996 General Files also contains annual reports, recruiting practices, strategic planning, and material related to various MEC programs and wider initiatives (such as the Michigan Integrated Food and Farming Systems group and Urban Core Mayors coalition). Likewise, the Issue Files in each sub-series contain background information (clippings, state government documents, publications, etc.), correspondence, testimony, and other content relating to issues addressed by the council and, to a lesser extent, its individual members.
  - 1980-1993
    (includes earlier background materials)
    - General files
      - MEC administration
        - General information (Box 1)
        - Filing system (Box 1)
        - Michigan Environmental Information Computer Access Network, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
        - MEC formation/history (Box 1)
        - Bylaws (Box 1)
      - MEC books/budget
        - Audit reports, 1985-1986; 1989 (Box 1)
        - Budget, 1984/1985-1986/1987; 1989-1990; 4 folders (Box 1)
        - Michigan Environmental Report memos, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
      - Lobbying/tax law, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
      - Grants/fundraising
        - Newsletter grant, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
        - Harder Foundation, 1984-1988 (Box 1)
        - Plans, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
        - Toxics grant (Mott Foundation), 1985 (Box 1)
        - Joyce Foundation, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
        - Plans, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
        - Fundraising strategy, 1983-1988; undated (Box 1)
      - Member organizations
        - West Michigan Environmental Action Council, 1977-1979; 1983-1988; 3 folders (Box 1)
        - East Michigan Environmental Action Council, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
        - Sierra Club Mackinac Chapter, 1982-1988 (Box 1)
        - Flint Environmental Action Team, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
        - Detroit Audubon Society, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
        - Michigan Audubon Society, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
        - Public Interest Research Group in Michigan, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
        - Trout Unlimited, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
        - Michigan Lake and Stream Associations, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
        - Upper Peninsula Environmental Coalition, 1984-1988 (Box 1)
        - Michigan Environmental Education Association, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
        - Ecology Center of Ann Arbor, 1984-1988 (Box 1)
        - Ecology Center of Ann Arbor Pesticide Task Force, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
        - Tip of the Mitt Watershed Council, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
        - Michigan Natural Areas Council, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
        - Northern Michigan Environmental Action Council, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
        - American Lung Association of Michigan, 1982-1988 (Box 2)
        - Citizens Against Chemical Contamination, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
        - League of Women Voters of Michigan, 1982-1988 (Box 2)
        - Council for Rural Awareness, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
      - Non-member organizations
        - Committee to Preserve Allegan Forest, 1983 (Box 2)
        - Safe Energy Coalition of Michigan, 1983-1987 (Box 2)
        - Michigan United Conservation Clubs, 1981-1987 (Box 2)
        - Waste Systems Institute, 1981-1986 (Box 2)
        - Great Lakes United, 1983-1988; 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Michigan Toxic Dumpsites Conference, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
        - Clinton River Watershed Council, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
        - Environmental Defense Fund, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
      - Issues management
        - Carol Dansereau notes, undated (Box 2)
        - Discussions with member organizations and others, 1983-1987 (Box 2)
        - MEC priorities, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
      - Conferences
        - Environmental Roundtable, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
        - Retreat, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
        - Summit, 1983 (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous, 1983-1988 (Box 2)
        - Strategy planning, 1985 (Box 2)
      - MEC publications: newsletters/memos, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
      - State executive branch
        - Governor's Office, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
        - Dept. of Natural Resources, 1980; 1987-1988 (Box 2)
        - Toxic Substances Control Commission, 1987 (Box 2)
        - Environmental Protection Policy Advisory Committee, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
        - Midwest Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact, 1986-1988; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Federal/regional/international commissions, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
      - U.S. Congress, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Issue files
      - Air
        - Miscellaneous, 1981-1988 (Box 3)
        - Acid rain, 1984-1988; undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
        - American Lung Association of Michigan Advisory Board, 1984-1989 (Box 3)
      - Administrative procedures/rulemaking, 1980-1987 (Box 3)
      - Dept. of Natural Resources budget, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
      - Energy
        - Hydro and miscellaneous, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
        - Nuclear power and waste, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
        - Wood, 1985-1987 (Box 3)
      - Enforcement
        - Barrels, Inc. (Lansing, Mich.) case, 1972-1986; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous, 1977; 1984-1988; undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Environment and economy, 1975-1985 (Box 3)
      - Great Lakes general, 1986-1988 (Box 3)
      - Hazardous waste management (Box 4)
      - Lands
        - Coastal zone management, 1989-1990; undated (Box 4)
        - Project ELF, 1982-1983 (Box 4)
        - Farmland loss, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
        - Forest management, 1984; 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Michigan Natural Resources Trust Fund, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
        - Natural rivers, 1976; 1982; 1986-1988 (Box 4)
        - Sand dunes, 1987-1990; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Wetlands
          - General, 1981; 1983; 1985-1990; undated; 5 folders (Box 4)
          - Great Lakes Wetlands Policy Consortium, 1988-1990; 3 folders (Box 5)
          - Wetlands Protection Act administrative rules, 1987-1988; 4 folders (Box 5)
          - Homestead case (Glen Arbor, Mich. golf course development)
            - Correspondence and reports, 1987-1989; 5 folders (Box 5)
            - Economic and fiscal impact study, 1987 (Box 5)
            - Environmental assessment, 1987 (Box 5)
            - Report (unidentified), 1988 (Box 5)
            - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
          - Wilderness/natural areas
            - General, 1983-1988; 2 folders (Box 5)
            - Nordhouse Dunes, 1984-1987; undated (Box 5)
      - Mining/drilling
        - Minerals in general
          - General, 1981-1985 (Box 5)
          - Metallic minerals lease policy, 1973; 1980-1982; undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
        - Coal, 1980-1983 (Box 5)
        - Oil and gas
          - General, 1971; 1980-1988; 3 folders (Box 5)
          - Great Lakes drilling ban, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
          - XNOX (Exploration not Exploitation) Committee, 1985-1987 (Box 6)
          - Study of severance tax increase, 1982 (Box 6)
        - Uranium, 1980-1983 (Box 6)
      - Pesticides, 1973-1988; 9 folders (Box 6)
      - Politics
        - Miscellaneous organizations, 1978-1983 (Box 6)
        - U.S. Congress environmental voting records, 1978-1982 (Box 6)
        - Michigan Legislature environmental voting records, 1972-1982 (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous candidates, 1982-1984 (Box 6)
      - Solid waste
        - General, 1981-1988 (Box 6)
        - Solid Waste Management Act rules, 1979-1984; 3 folders (Box 6)
        - Clean Michigan Fund, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
        - Solid Waste Management Planning Advisory Committee, 1980-1987 (Box 6)
        - Solid Waste Management Act amendments, 1981-1988; 4 folders (Box 6)
        - State solid waste strategy
          - General, 1980-1988 (Box 6)
          - Forum, November 1983
            - Background papers (Box 6)
            - General, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Solid waste bonding bill, 1984-1987 (Box 7)
        - Solid waste policy, 1979-1980; 1983; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Landfills
          - General, 1981-1988 (Box 7)
          - Richmond Township (Osceola County, Mich.) case, 1985-1988; 5 folders (Box 7)
        - Flow control, 1986 (Box 7)
        - Bottle Bill, 1979-1986; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Resource recovery, 1979-1988; 2 folders (Box 7)
        - County plans, 1979-1987 (Box 7)
        - Sewage management, 1983-1986 (Box 7)
        - Ad Hoc Committee on Waste Management, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
        - Incineration, 1984-1986; 8 folders (Box 7)
        - Appropriations, 1984-1986; 4 folders (Box 7)
        - St. Mary's Peerless Cement Co. case, 1987 (Box 7)
      - Toxics
        - Superfund, 1980; 1983-1987; 5 folders (Box 7)
        - Michigan's hazardous materials response plan, undated (Box 8)
        - Michigan Environmental Response Act, 1980-1988; 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Superfund/Michigan Environmental Response Act sites, 1982-1988; 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Liquid Disposal, Inc., case, 1987-1988 (Box 8)
        - Rose Township-Demode Road case, 1987 (Box 8)
        - South Macomb Disposal Authority case, 1987; 2 folders (Box 8)
        - State Superfund initiative, 1989 (Box 8)
        - Hooker Chemicals case, 1977; 1979-1981; 3 folders (Box 8)
        - Torch Lake case, 1981-1984 (Box 8)
        - Chemical registration bills, 1979-1981; 1983; 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Water contamination, 1982-1987 (Box 8)
        - Charlevoix municipal well case, 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Critical materials register, 1983-1985 (Box 8)
        - Toxic Substance Control Commission, 1982-1987; 4 folders (Box 8)
        - Toxic Education Citizens Action Program, 1983-1984 (Box 8)
        - PCBs, 1984-1986 (Box 8)
        - Advisories, 1984-1987 (Box 8)
        - Miscellaneous, 1980-1987; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Transportation
        - Miscellaneous, 1981-1983; 1988 (Box 8)
        - Grand Rapids Southbelt, 1980-1982 (Box 8)
        - I-69 (Eaton County), 1974-1982 (Box 9)
        - M-275 (Oakland County), 1977-1980 (Box 9)
      - Urban environment, 1980-1982; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Water
        - Clean Water Act reauthorization, 1983-1985 (Box 9)
        - Drain code, 1978-1983 (Box 9)
        - Dam Safety Act, 1985 (Box 9)
        - Groundwater
          - Contamination sites, 1982-1987 (Box 9)
          - Underground storage tanks, 1981-1988 (Box 9)
          - Environmental impairment liability insurance, 1981-1984; 4 folders (Box 9)
          - Brine/Salt, 1981-1986; 6 folders (Box 9)
          - Governor's strategy, 1984-1985 (Box 9)
          - Deep well injection, 1980-1987; 2 folders (Box 9)
          - Background for Carol Dansereau think tank speech, 1984 (Box 9)
          - Miscellaneous, 1983-1988; 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Inland lakes and streams, 1980-1984 (Box 9)
        - Dredge and fill, 1982-1986; 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Great Lakes diversions, 1983-1988; 3 folders (Box 9)
        - Water rights, 1980-1983; 5 folders (Box 10)
        - Water quality management, 1980-1990; 4 folders (Box 10)
        - Discharge of carcinogens, 1977-1987; 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Wildlife
        - Hunting bills, 1982-1987; 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Endangered species, 1985-1986 (Box 10)
        - Snagging, 1980-1984; 3 folders (Box 10)
        - Cruelty to animals, 1980-1987 (Box 10)
        - Falconry, 1981-1985 (Box 10)
        - Nongame wildlife check off program, 1980-1986; 6 folders (Box 10)
      - Work place right to know (Community right to know), 1982-1988; 8 folders (Box 10)
  - 1993-1996
    (includes earlier background material)
    - General files
      - Administration
        - Annual reports, 1993-1995 (Box 11)
        - Brochures, 1994 (Box 11)
        - Budget, 1993-1994 (Box 11)
        - Committee assignments, 1988 (Box 11)
        - Land use initiatives, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
        - New and potential members, 1989; 1993-1996 (Box 11)
        - Operating plans, 1990-1995 (Box 11)
        - Positions available, 1993 (Box 11)
        - Public service announcements, 1995 (Box 11)
        - Strategic planning, 1989 (Box 11)
      - Conferences
        - Legislative luncheons, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
        - Michigan Environmental Council Congress' environmental retreat, 1983; 1991 (Box 11)
        - Open space and development (Richard Arendt), 1995 (Box 11)
      - Farm-A-Syst, 1994 (Box 11)
      - Grassroots groups, 1989-1994 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Farmland and Agricultural Development Task Force, 1994-1995 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Integrated Food and Farming Systems (MIFFS)
        - Annual report, 1994-1995 (Box 11)
        - Farmland preservation site meetings, 1995 (Box 11)
        - Memo (Newsletter), 1995 (Box 11)
        - Miscellaneous, 1994-1995 (Box 11)
        - Traveling seminar, 1995 (Box 11)
      - Michigan RIM project, 1994 (Box 11)
      - Michigan Sea Grant College Program, 1994-1995 (Box 11)
      - Opinion surveys, 1995 (Box 11)
      - Southeast Michigan Initiatives (SEMI), 1996 (Box 11)
      - State government
        - Corporate clean citizens initiative, 1996 (Box 11)
        - Department of Environmental Quality, 1995-1996 (Box 11)
        - Department of Natural Resources
          - Budget, 1982-1991 (Box 11)
          - Management plan, 1991-1992 (Box 11)
          - Miscellaneous, 1996 (Box 11)
          - Ombudsman selection, 1990 (Box 11)
        - Governor's office (Engler), 1993-1996 (Box 11)
        - Low level radiation waste, 1985-1995; 7 folders (Box 12)
        - Open government act, 1994-1995 (Box 12)
        - Pollution self audits, 1995-1996 (Box 12)
      - Urban Core Mayors, 1994-1995 (Box 12)
    - Issue files
      - Air
        - Clean Air Act, 1993-1996 (Box 12)
        - Emissions, 1992 (Box 12)
        - Pollution, 1988-1991 (Box 12)
      - Energy
        - Electric integrated resource plan, 1989 (Box 12)
        - Oil and gas, 1995-1996 (Box 12)
        - Oil and gas association and advisory boards, 1989-1991 (Box 12)
        - Palisades nuclear power plant, 1992-1994 (Box 12)
      - Environmental education, 1971-1991 (Box 12)
      - Environmental justice (racism), 1992-1995 (Box 12)
      - Gypsy moth, 1991 (Box 12)
      - Lands
        - Coastal zone management
          - Coastal Watcher's Report newsletter submissions, 1995 (Box 12)
          - Data sources, 1985-1995; 2 folders (Box 12)
          - Frenchtown Charter Township Resort district authority, 1991; 1994 (Box 12)
          - Miscellaneous, 1989-1995; 3 folders (Box 12)
        - Detroit Greenways, 1995 (Box 12)
        - Forests, 1993-1994 (Box 12)
        - Golf courses, 1991-1994 (Box 12)
        - High risk erosion areas, 1990-1994 (Box 12)
        - Homestead case (Glen Arbor, MI golf course development), 1991-1996; 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Huron Land Use Alliance, 1995 (Box 12)
        - Off road vehicles damage, 1994-1996 (Box 13)
        - Purchase of development rights, 1990-1995 (Box 13)
        - Saginaw Bay watershed initiatives, 1993-1995 (Box 13)
        - Sand dunes
          - Miscellaneous, 1986-1995 (Box 13)
          - Nordhouse dunes, 1988-1995 (Box 13)
        - Sludge, 1997; 1990-1991 (Box 13)
        - State parks, 1992-1994 (Box 13)
        - Wetlands
          - Conservation reserve program, 1995 (Box 13)
          - Protection ordinances, S.B. 522, 1980-1993 (Box 13)
        - Woodland Meadows, 1992-1993 (Box 13)
      - Lawn care, 1995 (Box 13)
      - Pesticides, 1991-1993 (Box 13)
      - Pesticides ordinances, 1985-1996 (Box 13)
      - Pollution prevention
        - Funding, 1996 (Box 13)
        - Miscellaneous, 1985-1991 (Box 13)
        - Program, 1994-1996 (Box 13)
      - Solid waste
        - Bottle bill, 1989-1991 (Box 13)
        - Carleton Farms, 1994-1995 (Box 13)
        - Combined sewer overflow, 1987-1991 (Box 13)
        - County-wide solid waste management plans (Act 641), 1988-1990; 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Environmental protection fees, 1981-1992 (Box 13)
        - Incineration, 1989-1993 (Box 13)
        - Landfills, 1987 (Box 13)
        - Management, 1978-1996; 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Paper mills, 1984-1990 (Box 13)
        - Quality of Life bond proposal, 1988 (Box 13)
        - Recycling, 1988-1994; 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Toxics
        - Batteries, 1990 (Box 14)
        - Cement kilns, 1996 (Box 14)
        - Clean up criteria, 1995 (Box 14)
        - Critical materials register, 1987; 1993-1996 (Box 14)
        - Dow, Project XL, 1988-1996 (Box 14)
        - Gage Industries--Ferndale, MI, 1991 (Box 14)
        - Gelman Chemical, 1988-1995 (Box 14)
        - Hazardous waste
          - Act 64, 1993 (Box 14)
          - Capacity plans, 1988-1989 (Box 14)
          - Management planning, circa 1990-1991 (Box 14)
          - PIRGIM report, 1989 (Box 14)
        - Lead, 1992-1996 (Box 14)
        - Military sites, 1991 (Box 14)
        - Miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 14)
        - PBB, 1979-1995 (Box 14)
        - Raco Missile Base (includes photos), 1985-1988 (Box 14)
        - Radon, 1988-1989 (Box 14)
        - Site reclamation, 1988-1993 (Box 14)
        - Superfund, 1993-1996 (Box 14)
        - Superfund sites, 1990-1993 (Box 14)
        - Toxic Substance Control Commission, 1979-1984 (Box 14)
      - Transportation, 1993; 1995 (Box 14)
      - Water
        - Contamination, 1994-1995 (Box 14)
        - Great Lakes diversions, 1988-1994 (Box 14)
        - Great Lakes initiatives, 1990-1997 (Box 14)
        - Groundwater
          - Deep well injection, 1991-1993 (Box 14)
          - Education, 1991-1993 (Box 14)
          - Ingham County, 1992-1993 (Box 14)
          - Leaking Underground Storage Tank Stakeholders (LUST), 1987-1995; 2 folders (Box 14)
          - Miscellaneous, 1986-1993; 2 folders (Box 14)
        - Lake Superior program, 1991 (Box 15)
        - Lake Superior toxic freeze, 1994 (Box 15)
        - Right to Farm act, 1991 (Box 15)
        - Rivers, 1992-1993 (Box 15)
        - Spills response, 1991 (Box 15)